A Guide to the Allan Gianniny Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Allan Gianniny Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
15075
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions
Acquisition Information
The papers were an internal transfer from the Science and Engineering Library, 2010 September 1.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Gianniny was professor emeritus of humanities (and technology, culture, and communication) at the University of Virginia from as early as 1969. He held numerous degrees, including a Bachelor of Science degree in Education, and a doctorate in Education.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of the office papers of University of Virginia Professor of Humanities, and Science, Omer Allan "Al" Gianniny from 1949 to 1996 and is about 450 items, 4 Hollinger boxes and less than 2 linear feet. Professor Gianniny was very interested in the history of the University and the collection contains many papers on the history of the School of Engineering and Applied Science (1836-1996) including several biographies of early professors such as Dean John "Jack" Egan Gibson, Edgar A. Starke, Jr., and William S. Weedon. There is also a photocopied manuscript by William Mynn Thornton; articles about William Barton Rogers and Leopold Jules Boeck; and a typescript of an interview with Charles Henderson. There are also log sheets of expenses for the University of Virginia airport administration building.
There is also information about the teaching of humanities to the students in the School of Engineering which was a tradition of the early professors, such as William Thornton. Professor Gianniny and Professor Joseph L. Vaughan were inspired by the early professors to give students a liberal arts education even though they were science students. The collection contains correspondence of Vaughan including questionnaires to corporations about the value of the UVA graduates education in English and its impact on their employment.
Other items include a letter from President Alderman to Paul Barringer, when he was president of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (History of SEAS Box 3, folder: 5;) a dissertation on Thomas Jefferson and public transportation; and a miscellaneous article on Claudius Crozet (Articles Box:1, folder: 2). There are also many photographs of the University taken by Joseph L. Vaughan including pictures of UVA boxing coach John LaRowe with Vaughan and other students, and photographs of the University science buildings and airfields from 1906 to 1935.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic
Contents List
- 1974-1978 Articles, 18 items (Box-folder 1:1)
  There are articles related to science
- 1836-1908; 1936 Articles, 11 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  There are articles by and about early science professors at the University of Virginia. There is also a miscellaneous article on Claudius Crozet by Colonel William Couper (1936)
- 1969-1975 Articles and Papers by Omer Allan Gianniny, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1984 December Article notes about the Rotunda by Omer Allan Gianniny, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1869; 1971; 1973; 1982; 1995 Canals, 7 items (Box-folder 1:5)
  There are articles about the Marshall Tunnel and the Kanawha Canal, and lecture notes of Professor Leopold Jules Boeck on canal navigation. Also included is an article on nineteenth century Swiss road signs
- n. d. Class handouts, 8 items (Box-folder 1:6)
- 1990; 1998 Class (seminar) on Jefferson and Science, 27 items (Box-folder 1:7)
  Included is a typescript of an interview by Earl Thornton of Professor Gianniny regarding Thomas Jefferson and his influence on engineering at the University of Virginia
- 1992 Correspondence of School of Engineering Faculty, 14 items (Box-folder 1:9)
  Correspondence about Applied Mathematics Instruction in the School of Engineering
- 1946-1994 Correspondence Allan Gianniny, 5 items (Box-folder 1:8)
  Included is a letter from Dean Walter S. Rodman informing Gianniny that he could return to school (after the war)
- n. d. Dissertation on Thomas Jefferson and Public Transportation, 1 item (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1941 History of the School of Engineering and Applied Science (SEAS): airport expenditures log, 1 item (Box-folder 2:2)
  There is a list of expenses for repairs and supplies for the airport building
- n. d. History of SEAS: Leopold Jules Boeck, 1 item (Box-folder 2:3)
- 1973-1983 History of SEAS: John "Jack" Egan Gibson, 10 items (Box-folder 2:4)
  There are biographies of Dean Gibson, ninth Dean of the School of Engineering and Applied Science. There are also three annual reports (notebooks) submitted by G. A. McAlpine
- 1972; 1977 History of SEAS: Charles Henderson interview transcripts, 2 items (Box-folder 2:5)
  There are two typed transcripts of interviews with Professor Charles Henderson by Charles Papazian who was writing his thesis on the History of the School of Engineering (also see Box 3 Thesis by Papazian)
- 1986 March History of SEAS 1836-1986, 1/2 notebook (Box-folder 2:6)
  "From Natural Philosophy to Applied Science," a history by Gianniny for the 150 year celebration
- 1986 March History of SEAS 1836-1986, 2/2 notebook (Box-folder 2:7)
- 1986 March History of SEAS 1836-1986, 1 notebook (Box-folder 2:8)
  "From Natural Philosophy to Applied Science," a history by Gianniny for the 150 year celebration; Appendix
- 1985 History of SEAS, 4 items (Box-folder 3:1)
  There is correspondence about planning a 150 year exhibit and celebration. There are early articles on science possibly for use in the exhibit, "How To Draw A Straight Line," by A. B. Kempe, and "An Elementary Treatise on Mechanics" by Augustus W. Smith.
- 1995 History of SEAS: 1819-1994, 1/2 notebook (Box-folder 3:2)
  "From Technical Philosophy to Applied Science," a history by Gianniny
- 1995 History of SEAS: 1819-1994, 2/2 notebook (Box-folder 3:3)
- n. d. History of SEAS: History of Engineering Science and Systems Developing a Graduate School, 1 notebook (Box-folder 3:4)
- 1911; 1936; 1977 History of SEAS, 13 items (Box-folder 3:5)
  There is a short history of the School of Engineering by T. Graham Hereford and Allan Gianniny, Jr. and a history of the technology in engineering education by Bruce E. Seely Included is a letter from President [Alderman] to Paul Barringer (President of Virginia Polytechnic Institute) about a discussion and report of the Educational Commission of Virginia. Alderman tried to correct Barringer by saying that the report was formed from a group of opinions and was not the representation of only Dr. Thornton.
- 1968 History of SEAS: Humanities Development Project, 17 items (Box-folder 3:6)
  Humanities were very important to the early science professors at UVA and later professors wanted to carry on the tradition of teaching english to science students. Included is a Report to the Old Dominion Advisory Committee regarding humanities and several articles on the importance of teaching the humanities.
- 1976 History of SEAS: Long Range Planning Reports Division of Humanities, 2 items (Box-folder 3:7)
- n. d. History of SEAS: John Lloyd Newcomb, # items (Box-folder 3:8)
- 1838; n. d. History SEAS: William Barton Rogers, 2 items (Box-folder 3:9)
  There is an article about Rogers teaching methods and a photocopy of his article "An Elementary Treatise on The Strength of Materials"
- 1995 July 12 History of SEAS: Edgar A. Starke, Jr., 2 items (Box-folder 4:1)
  There are two copies of a manuscript on the history of Professor Starke written by Allan Gianniny, Jr.
- 1941 History of SEAS: Teaching English in the School of Engineering and Applied Science, 55 items (Box-folder 4:2)
  There is correspondence with Joseph L. Vaughan including his questionnaire regarding the level of English instruction needed for science students. Included are answers from corporations such as DuPont, General Electric, as well as alumni from the University
- 1933; 1938; 1944 History of SEAS: Teaching English in Science Programs-Articles, 23 items (Box-folder 4:3)
  History of SEAS: Teaching English in Science Programs-Articles
- 1926 History of SEAS: William Mynn Thornton "Engineering Instruction in the University of Virginia", 4 items (Box-folder 4:4)
  Included is a typescript photocopy of Professor Thornton's manuscript
- n. d. History of SEAS: Charles Scott Venable, 1 item (Box-folder 4:5)
- 1979 History of SEAS: William S. Weedon English in the School of Engineering, 1 item (Box-folder 4:6)
  There is a memo from Allan Gianniny Jr. to Dean John "Jack" Gibson that describes William "Bill" S. Weedon. It particularly recognizes Weedon's work as being instrumental in developing English instruction in the School of Engineering.
- 1935 Photographs of the School of Engineering and Applied Science, 104 items (Box-folder 4:7)
- 1935 Photographs John La Rowe, 6 items (Box-folder 4:9)
- n. d.; 1986 Photocopies of photographs, 48 items (Box-folder 4:11)
  There is also some correspondence about the engineering education exhibit (1986)
- n. d. Negatives of photographs, 50 items (Box-folder 4:12)
- 1980 Research and statistics for the School of Engineering and Applied Science, 1 notebook (Box-folder 4:13)
- 1996 Strategic Plans for the School of Engineering and Applied Science, 1 notebook (Box-folder 4:14)
- 1972 Thesis "History and Development of Engineering Education at the University of Virginia" by Charles Papazian, 1 item (Box-folder 4:15)